<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Jtoll</title><link>http://jtoll.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Jtoll</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 08:16:20 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://jtoll.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Volatility Harvesting</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-harvesting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 08:16:20 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-harvesting/</guid><description>&lt;p>An intriguing read, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1508.05241">Volatility Harvesting: Extracting Return From Randomness&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; covering a range of topics including volatility pumping, volatility harvesting, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parrondo%27s_paradox">Parrondo&amp;rsquo;s Paradox&lt;/a>, and Shannon&amp;rsquo;s Demon.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Volatility as an Asset Class</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-as-an-asset-class/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 12:02:53 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-as-an-asset-class/</guid><description>&lt;p>A nice overview of the cyclical nature of volatility trading by Jonathan Kinlay entitled, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://jonathankinlay.com/index.php/2015/06/case-volatility/">The Case for Volatility as an Asset Class&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;. For options traders, the idea of volatility as an asset class is taken for granted. For most others, it&amp;rsquo;s likely they&amp;rsquo;ve never given these strategies much of a thought. That&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate given the excellent diversification (i.e. uncorrelated returns) provided by most volatility strategies.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Systematic Scalping: A reference approach to daily gamma scalping</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/systematic-scalping/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 15:37:57 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/systematic-scalping/</guid><description>&lt;p>As a follow-up to my previous article on &lt;a href="http://jtoll.com/post/gamma-scalping-cy/">&amp;ldquo;Gamma Scalping Cypress Semiconductor&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>, I take a look at an alternative approach to gamma scalping. The initial article elicited many questions regarding the timing or triggers that prompt delta hedging. In this article I compare our initial, ad lib hedging results with a more systematic strategy that hedges (i.e. neutralizes) the position delta once-a-day at the closing price. This more systematic approach will serve as a reference to evaluate the efficacy of the ad lib approach to hedging.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Love Gamma? Where to find the highest gamma to theta ratio</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/love-gamma/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 14:38:21 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/love-gamma/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re an options traders that likes to get a lot of bang for your buck, here are two things to look for in an underlying security that can help maximize the ratio of gamma to theta in your options position.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When To Hedge Delta: Why There's No Good Answer</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/when-to-hedge-delta/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 15:38:03 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/when-to-hedge-delta/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the course of explaining delta-neutral trading strategies, the question that inevitably arises is when to hedge the net position delta. It&amp;rsquo;s a great question, but a question with no good (i.e. definite) answer.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Theta: A Detailed Look at the Decay of Option Time Value</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/theta/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 14:08:13 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/theta/</guid><description>&lt;p>Of all the option sensitivities, or Greeks, there is likely none that is obsessed over by beginning options traders as much as theta. It seems that this obsession largely stems from a fear that they might be the sucker that gets stuck owning some rotting, soon-to-be worthless option contract. Given all this obsessing, one might expect a better understanding of theta. Unfortunately, many beginning and experienced option traders alike fall prey to generalities concerning the nature of theta. Hopefully this article will provide some insight into the specifics of time decay.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Volatility, Price and Delta: The Effects of Implied Volatility and Underlying Price on Delta</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-price-and-delta/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2015 12:31:47 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-price-and-delta/</guid><description>&lt;p>For options traders trying to understand how the value of an option might change given a change to one of the pricing model components, the obvious source for answers are the option sensitivities, otherwise known as the &amp;ldquo;Greeks&amp;rdquo;. What&amp;rsquo;s not as well know is that there are second-order sensitivities that can help explain how these first-order sensitivities change given a change to one of the pricing components. &amp;ldquo;Vanna&amp;rdquo; is a second-order sensitivity which describes the change in delta given a change in volatility.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gamma Scalping Cypress Semiconductor: An Example of Trading a Delta Neutral, Long Gamma Options Position</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/gamma-scalping-cy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 16:07:11 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/gamma-scalping-cy/</guid><description>&lt;p>In one of today&amp;rsquo;s option mentoring sessions, one of the topics covered was the process of gamma scalping a delta neutral, long gamma options position. The client was having some difficulty thoroughly understanding the concept. To better explore the topic, we decided to simulate a very simple long gamma options position in &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/quote/CY:US">Cypress Semiconductor (CY)&lt;/a>, and then to gamma scalp the underlying security, keeping the net position delta neutral.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vertical Spread Parity: (Or why there's nothing special about credit vertical spreads)</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/vertical-spread-parity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 13:25:05 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/vertical-spread-parity/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the first spreading strategies normally taught to beginning options investors is the vertical spread. This is a spread between two calls (or two puts) with the same expiration date, but differing strike prices. The strategy gets its name from the fact that the prices for each leg of the spread are typically listed vertically, one above the other, on a traders screen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a basic option strategy, but it has many desirable qualities, not the least of which is a clear and easy to define risk/reward profile. It tends to be a popular strategy amongst options newsletters. Unfortunately, many newsletters seem to suggest only trading vertical spreads in certain ways, or seem to imply that certain vertical spread strategies are superior to others. The fact is that there&amp;rsquo;s no secret sauce. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing special about selling (credit) vertical spreads that makes it more profitable than buying (debit) vertical spreads. In fact, it can be easily shown that they&amp;rsquo;re effectively the same strategy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Duel of the Deltas: Calculating Moneyness via Dual Delta</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/duel-of-the-deltas/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 11:14:57 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/duel-of-the-deltas/</guid><description>&lt;p>You would have to search long and hard to find an options trader who isn&amp;rsquo;t familiar with the concept of delta. As one of the most basic option sensitivities, or &amp;ldquo;Greeks&amp;rdquo;, delta expresses the relationship between the value of the option and the value of the underlying security. Secondarily, the delta is also sometimes used as an ad lib approximation of the percentage chance that an option will expire in the money. While this can be a quick and useful approximation, it&amp;rsquo;s not as accurate as many believe it to be. To correctly calculate the percentage chance that an option will expire in the money, one has to calculate what&amp;rsquo;s known as the &amp;ldquo;Dual Delta&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rule of Sixteen</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/rule-of-16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 10:19:46 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/rule-of-16/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volatility_(finance)#Crude_volatility_estimation">Rule of Sixteen&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; is a simple approximation used by option traders to quickly get an idea of the potential move a particular underlying security might make. As a quick example, suppose it&amp;rsquo;s a day before expiration and you&amp;rsquo;re trying to determine how concerned you should be about covering a position of out of the money options. The Rule of Sixteen says that with an implied volatility of 32 there is about a 2/3rds chance that the underlying will move 2% or less in that one remaining day. One out of every three days the underlying will move more than 2%.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Path Independence of Volatility</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/path-independence-of-volatility/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 16:11:32 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/path-independence-of-volatility/</guid><description>&lt;p>Volatility is undoubtably one of the most important aspects of option trading. Although the basic idea of calculating historical volatility as the annualized standard deviation of a series of lognormal close to close price returns is fairly simple, there exist a broad range of adaptations of this general idea in an attempt to glean additional insight and efficiency from market data. Nonetheless, this traditional method of calculating volatility is still in wide use due to the simplicity of its calculation and the intuitive nature of its insights.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Volatility of VIX</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-of-vix/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 17:44:37 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/volatility-of-vix/</guid><description>&lt;p>The S&amp;amp;P 500 index &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/quote/SPX:IND">(SPX)&lt;/a> has been down five of the past six trading sessions and along with that has come a significant increase in the &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/quote/VIX:IND">VIX&lt;/a> implied volatility index. But the most interesting aspect of the selloff is not the current level of the VIX, but the size of the increase and the speed with which it&amp;rsquo;s taken place, or in other words, the volatility of implied volatility.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sell Rosh Hashanah, Buy Yom Kippur?</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-rosh-hashanah/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 09:18:46 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-rosh-hashanah/</guid><description>&lt;p>With yesterday&amp;rsquo;s 1.6% sell off in the major indices, and the fact that it happened to coincide with the start of Rosh Hashanah, some traders were dredging up the &lt;a href="http://www.bespokeinvest.com/thinkbig/2013/9/4/sell-rosh-hashanah-buy-yom-kippur.html">&amp;ldquo;Sell Rosh Hashanah, Buy Yom Kippur&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> adage to try to the explain the market action. Like many of these old adages, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to know whether there&amp;rsquo;s any quantitive data that actually supports their use. Much of the time, even if these strategies did work at some time in the past, they rarely do today. But there&amp;rsquo;s no way to know without crunching the data, so that&amp;rsquo;s what we did.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sell in May? Redux: Another 30 Years</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-in-may-redux/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 16:58:11 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-in-may-redux/</guid><description>&lt;p>Following on yesterday’s post, I decided to extend our analysis back another 30 years to provide more context to the old adage of “Sell in May and go away”. Again, I&amp;rsquo;m using historical price data for the S&amp;amp;P 500 index &lt;a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/quote/SPX:IND">(SPX)&lt;/a>, but this time with data covering the 30 years from 1964 to 1993.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sell in May?</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-in-may/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 18:23:38 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/sell-in-may/</guid><description>&lt;p>The old adage says to “Sell in May and go away”. That’s simple enough, but it’s less clear when it’s the appropriate time to buy back in. Some traders suggest going long again after Labor Day, which is the first Monday in September. Others completely avoid historically treacherous October and stay away until the beginning of November, a full 6 months!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Decimal Time</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/decimal-time/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 15:40:27 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/decimal-time/</guid><description>&lt;p>My son wondered why we don&amp;rsquo;t have a more rational, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decimal_time">decimal&lt;/a> system for time. To explore the idea, we made a simple javascript clock implementing decimal time.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Half-normal Distribution</title><link>http://jtoll.com/post/half-normal-distribution/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 16:38:47 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://jtoll.com/post/half-normal-distribution/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Half-normal_distribution">half-normal distribution&lt;/a> is a special case of the folded normal distribution, where if X is a standard normal distribution, the absolute value of X is the half-normal distribution.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>